So, we're back and we'll edit this back
in. So, Bin Laden's family gave DNA.
They gave DNA [clears throat] and the
doctor had collected DNA from what
turned out to be Bin Laden's children.
Bin Laden had four wives. He had
children that ranged in age from like
six all the way up into their 40s. And
so, uh, the CIA was able to confirm that
these were bin Laden's children. They
lived in the house with the 20ft wall.
Therefore, the man walking in circles in
the backyard was most likely Osama bin.
>> What was the or because you were out of
the CIA at that time, but you were
working for like Fox News as a
contributor or or ABC
>> and you knew that we sent a doctor over
and
>> Well, I'll tell you what, Brian Ross
called me that that night and he said,
um, something's going on at the White
House. I said like
>> Oh, the day that they Okay. Okay.
>> Yeah. I said like what? He said, I don't
know. that's why I'm calling you. He
said, "The president just called a press
conference for 10:00." And I said, "At
night?" And he said, "Yeah." I said,
"They got bin Laden." He said, "That's
why I was calling." Do you think that's
what this would be? I said, "Yeah, they
would not call a press conference for
anybody beneath Bin Laden. This has to
be about Bin Laden." And so I went into
the studio. I got dressed and went into
studio waiting for the story to break.
And then it broke and I was on all night
long. I left the studio 7 o'clock the
next morning, slept for a few hours and
went back to the studio again.
>> Real quick and then we'll transit. Did
the Pakistanians, they knew he was
there.
>> You know, I'm of the belief that it
would have been impossible for the most
wanted man in the world to live a half a
mile from the Pakistani version of West
Point. Abidabad is named after a British
major named Abbott, right?
>> Okay.
>> He was there. He was the first military
trainer in Pakistan when Pakistan became
a country in 1947.
So the whole city of Abidabad is just
military military
>> right
>> and it's a nice city.
>> It's a nice city. It it's not like the
[__] holes you know that people see on
television. Karach uh Lahore Fisab.
Pashau. It's a nice place and and it's
where the leaders of the of the
Pakistani military all live. And
>> so yeah, I think it was it would have
been impossible for them not to know
that he was there.
>> What do you think the mood was like at
the CIA when we got him?
>> Jubilation.
>> Yes.
>> Promotions. But did you know
>> promotions, medals? Yeah.
>> The I'm curious. Nobody asked this
question. No, nobody. Well, if they do,
where did the lady get to? The redheaded
lady, you know. No, I've I've Googled
some names have popped up and I [__]
forget, you know, cuz you can. Now, the
one late Now, did you see the Get Bin
Laden documentary?
>> There was a lady that was on there, but
they blackened her face out. Now, I'm
not
>> Which is hilarious. I'm not the smartest
[__] you know, I'm not the sharpest
tool in the shed, but I would bet on
Kalashi. Hey, if that if was that the
head of the CIA that found Bin Lan, I
would I would lay a hundred on it that
that was her and she was talking and
they Was that her?
>> Have you know?
>> Yeah.
>> And then there was a lady with the curly
hair that's kind of like heavier set.
Did you have any experiences with her?
All nice girls?
>> No.
>> No. They were all demons.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. cuz the one was against torture.
The one, you know, was crying tears and
and uh what whatnot. And cuz they were
talking about uh Jennifer Matthews who
died. And I don't mean no disrespect,
but uh I've listened to not just you,
but Rob,
>> the guy that, you know, supposedly shot
Bin L said that that lady was [__]
getting people going to get people
killed. The third commander at Seal Team
Six said, "Stay the [__] away from her.
She will get you killed."
>> Jennifer, the CIA killed Jennifer. And
I'll tell you how
>> I want to ask what I mean about what I
mean by that
>> with Al Bellow.
>> We've got rules.
>> We got rules for promotion at the CIA.
When you when you when you want to be
promoted from GS15, which is the highest
level in the general services scale to
the senior intelligence service, right?
Like you're the directors.
>> What's the bump if you don't mind me
asking in pay from G15 to senior
intelligence?
>> G15 to to SIS is probably 25 grand.
>> Okay. So decent. Decent. Yeah. But if
you're in the senior intelligence
service, you always you also get these
like these corporate style bonuses,
>> okay,
>> every year that the rest of us don't
get.
>> So if you want to be eligible for
promotion from GS15 to SIS1,
>> um you have to have done at least one
tour in another directorate. The CIA's
four directorates, operations,
intelligence, science, and technology,
and administration.
And you have to have done a tour in the
policy community which is either state
or DoD.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So, Jennifer was
an analyst. She was in the director of
intelligence. She had done a policy tour
at the State Department, but she needed
an operational
assignment
>> to check the box.
>> To check the box.
>> So, they said, "Jennifer, do you want to
be chief of base host?" and she's like,
"Absolutely, yes."
>> It's a dangerous place, right?
>> It's a very dangerous place. It's out in
the middle of nowhere in the mountains
of Afghanistan.
And
>> she did not have the time to go through
the operational training or the security
training. And they said, "Don't worry
about that. You're going to be fine.
Just go out there and, you know, let's
let's do it." Well, that was an
incredible disservice.
She didn't know anything about
recruiting spies to steal secrets. She
didn't know anything about keeping her
people safe. There were more than a
dozen people working for her. She didn't
know anything about keeping herself
safe. She had never been operational
before. And so
at the same time that Jennifer was going
out to host,
a spy was walking into the American
consulate in Istanbul
and he said, "I'm Jordanian. I'm a
doctor, but more importantly, I am Osama
bin Laden's personal doctor.
>> Was that true?
>> Yes.
>> This was a major break in the case.
>> Okay.
>> So,
he did not want to be interrogated, he
did not want to be debriefed in
Istanbul. He said, "I have to go back to
Jordan, but then I'm I'm on my way back
to Afghanistan because Bin Laden has
requested that I be back." We're like,
"Okay, we'll meet you in Afghanistan.
Come to host, come to uh the base, I
think it was called Chapman, and uh
we'll we'll uh talk to you there." Okay.
Red flags with neon lights should have
been going.
>> Why is this guy got to go back? Why Why
wouldn't he debrief there? I mean, yeah.
>> Why wasn't he polygraphed?
>> Yeah.
>> Why wasn't he surveiled?
>> Surveiled,
>> right? Why couldn't he meet in Istanbul?
Why couldn't he meet in Aman? If he's
Jordanian and his family's Jordanian,
>> why did he have to meet in Kost even if
he had to go back to Afghanistan?
>> Why couldn't he meet inside the US
embassy in Kabell?
>> So, Jennifer, God bless her. Jennifer
was the only one of those. It was this
click of of five women in the
counterterrorism center. She was the
only one that I didn't hate.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Yeah. Um, the others were bloodthirsty
monsters,
including the red-headed devil.
>> Well, you don't call somebody the
red-headed devil for shits and giggles.
Pardon my French.
>> She's a monster.
>> Wow.
>> So,
Jennifer, because she was a sweet lady,
realized as she's going through the file
that this doctor, the day that he's
coming to host, it happens to be his
birthday.
So, she bakes him a cake.
She bakes him a cake and she tells
everybody in the in the base, "Hey,
listen. Let's meet him at his car and
we'll present him with the cake and
we'll sing happy birthday to him." Well,
first of all, nobody has frisked the
guy.
Secondly, the car pulls up outside the
hard line.
And
>> what is the hard line for our viewers
that don't know?
>> The hard line is the area that's
fortified, right? We've got sandbags,
we've got, you know, guns, we have
bulletproof glass, we have, you know,
steel doors.
>> Okay.
>> To protect you.
She takes everybody outside the hardline
past the metal detector.
And it didn't strike anybody as odd that
when he got out of the car, number one,
he was wearing winter clothes
>> and it was summer.
>> It was hot.
>> Okay.
>> The winter clothes were to conceal the
bomb that he had strapped.
>> Yes.
>> On himself.
And they didn't think it was odd that
when I he got out of the car, he was
quietly praying under his breath.
Why are you praying?
And then when she got everybody right up
to him to sing happy birthday, he blew
himself up and he killed Jennifer and
six other officers.
>> It was the deadliest day in the history
of CIA.
>> On that documentary that they did, they
actually played a video. I don't know if
it was an act or if it was the real guy
showing him meeting with Al video saying
he was going to you know meet the US and
they thought that he was a friendly but
this is not the watch this is detonator
you know they they show that in the
documentary
and
so he was a double agent correct
>> yeah he was a double agent
>> and just went bad right I'm going
>> I wouldn't even say he went bad I think
that the point from the beginning was to
kill as many CIA people as possible.
>> That was set out and they come up with
this plan. Hey, you're the doctor.
>> You can go. Yeah, of course. Because we
wanted Bin Laden so bad,
>> we would do. She probably thought, oh,
if this guy is who he says he is, that's
medals.
>> She's going to end up being the director
of the CIA. This guy is who he says he
is.
>> Yeah. She's going right to the top.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> And I sat next to Jennifer. She was a
very sweet person.
>> Wow. Um, she was working with some
sharks and they didn't give a [__] about
her safety.
>> Not at all.
>> Wow.
>> Mhm.
>> That's sad.
>> Cuz she has a family. I mean, I don't
know.
>> She had the best time recollection, she
had three daughters.
>> She had kids, a husband, and and you
know, and and I don't know, like I said,
the documentary is on Netflix, you know,
and because it become a money maker.
every everybody that was on that
documentary was had a feature of them in
you know zero dark 30 which you know
there's actually something interesting
and then we'll switch to another topic
but there was a guy and I'll say his
name because he was out on Sean Ryan
show Matt Bites now he was on 60 Minutes
and supposedly he killed Bin Laden
>> there are three different
>> and he was I don't know who the other
guy is I only know the Rob O'Neal I mean
>> made a living just
>> a living. I have a book the operator I
mean hey I I brought it and said hey you
know pay 50 bucks or you know hey what
whatever you know and
beset you know talks about how after the
bin Laden mission they went and there
was Leon Petta and I forget that the
director and producer is here dark 30
and Leon Panetta is like hey this is so
and so
>> written about this he outed them
>> he's going to make you f they're going
to make you f yeah I guess they gave him
a list of their name they actually
>> he read the he read the list of names to
a a group of unclassified audience
members
>> and gave them like the mockup that they
had the mockup the
>> classified mockup
>> classified.
>> I wrote an oped for the for the Los
Angeles Times.
>> Where would I find that at if I'm
>> Oh, it's it's still on the Times.
>> Okay. Would love to read it.
>> And I was like, why isn't Leon Petta in
prison?
>> Yeah,
>> right. This is a violation of the
Espionage Act.
>> Yeah,
>> you can't just talk about this stuff.
It's above top secret. And that made
being in the milit which I think hey I
we we live in the greatest country ever
and I respect people that serve this
country. It made the special forces look
real sexy. See it next thing you know
there's a [__] Seal Team 6 uh show on
CBS to where they're using Navy Seals to
consult on the show.
>> See, and their identities are supposed
to be perpetually classified.
>> They're not. Now everybody's making
money writing books. Like I said about
the guy that wrote Kil Bin Laden, he
used a pen name and and whatnot. I guess
that's was what you were supposed to do.
But you know, if you get a chance, watch
the interview with Besonette and Shawn
Ryan cuz he was ousted by the teams.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Was they were furious.
>> He wrote a book the same as Rob O'Neal,
but I guess he didn't get Yes.
bankrupted the guy.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, bankrupted the guy. And why
would they do that if they let the one
guy do it but not the other? Why? Why
would they?
I have no idea.
>> So
transitioning out of bin Laden, you
are famous for the capture of Abu Zaba.
So on the parag, you know, the you know
the org chart, you have Bin Laden. Where
was Abu Zeda?
>> You see that's kind of
>> that's what I want to transition into.
>> That's kind of the thing.
>> Everybody else transitions into Zeda to
bin Laden. I'm going to do it reverse
engineer.
>> We believed at the time that Abeda was
the number three in al-Qaeda. Okay.
>> He wasn't
>> really
>> he never joined al-Qaeda. He was a bad
guy. He had created al-Qaeda's safe
house in Pishaw, Pakistan, the house of
martyrs. He had created and staffed the
two training camps in southern
Afghanistan. He was kind of a
logistician. Like if you if you were
tired of fighting, you wanted to go
home, he would get you a passport and a
ticket, send you home. if you were brand
new, you just arrived and you wanted to
go fight, he'd get you across the
mountains into Afghanistan to be
trained. So, he was a bad guy, but he
had never pledged filty to Osama bin
Laden. And he had never joined al-Qaeda.
>> And he'd ever met Bin Laden.
>> No.
>> And how the hell did he get slid across
your desk if you can talk about that?
>> In retrospect, I wrote a book about it
with uh with Joe Hickman, who
>> who was Joe Hickman?
>> Joe Hickman was a a guy in the army who
had guarded Abaza at
>> Guantanamo. So I wrote half the book, he
wrote the other half the book, and it's
two whistleblowers accounts of, you
know, blah blah blah.
>> So
what really
put us on the wrong track with Auba
>> is that Abuza had a first cousin who was
also named Abu Zuba.
>> Really?
>> And we're getting these intelligence
reports like, "Oh my god, Abu Zuba is in
Pakistan. and he's going to do this this
operation. And then it's like, "Holy
[__] Abu Zuba is in in Jordan. He's
going to do this operation. Oh my god,
Abu Zuba is in Montana. Oh my god, Abu
Zuba is in Saudi Arabia. We didn't know
there were two Abu Zubas." And I
remember saying to a colleague of mine,
"This Abu Zuba, he's he's like some kind
of terrorist Superman. He's everywhere.
We just didn't know there were two of
them, not one." And then as soon as we
caught Abu Zuba in Fiselad,
his cousin who was in Montana
>> really was in
>> vanished.
>> Have they ever found him?
>> They never found him.
>> When you're going after Abu Zedu, you
land in Pakistan.
What What being a kid from Western
Pennsylvania who dreamed of of being a
spy in the Middle East. when you get
there and you know they say you you need
to cap was was your mission capture
average beta or capture as many al-qaeda
what whatever [clears throat]
>> we knew we were going to catch a lot of
people
>> in this in this series of raids he was
by far the most important target in fact
he was the very first what we called HBT
highv value
>> target
>> um in the war on terror and so as soon
as we got word that he was somewhere in
Pakistan and we had to catch him. Um,
we focused on him thinking
whoever else we get, it's going to be
gravy, but we had to get him because we
thought if we can get him. We had
already killed the number three in
al-Qaeda. That was Muhammad Atf.
>> We we bombed a house that he was hiding
in in Tora Bora. Oddly enough, when we
bombed the house, it it splintered the
dining room table and a chunk of wood
went through his neck and killed him.
So,
if Abu Zuba had been the number three,
we figured, well, he's only been the
number three since October, but he would
have been instrumental in the planning
of 9/11. He wasn't.
Now, he gave us deep actionable
intelligence later on to the to the FBI.
Intelligence that saved American lives
>> that you can't talk about.
>> Oh, no. I can tell you exactly what it
was.
>> Okay. What if you don't want to ask him?
>> He he gave us first of all the al-Qaeda
wiring diagram.
>> We had no idea how al-Qaeda was
structured. We knew Bin Laden was at the
top. Zawahi was at was number two.
Number three was vacant, constantly
changing person. But then under that, we
knew that the there were these cells.
There's, you know, there's Berlin and
and Koala Lumpur and Bangkok. And we
knew that there was al-Qaeda all over
the place, but we didn't know how they
operated or even whether they were in
communication with one another. So he
described it to us. So for example, this
is an example I use all the time.
Ali Sufan, the FBI interrogator.
>> He was on that dock. They they
>> a great guy.
>> Okay. Did
>> because I know you don't like the FBI.
>> I don't like but I love Ali. Okay.
>> He he did great work.
>> So
Ali would ask him if you were going to
do an operation in Dusseldorf,
how would you do that? And Aba would
say, well, I know this guy Muhammad and
he's the cell leader and here's his
phone number. and he's got a friend
Abdullah and Abdullah has access to
weapons. And here's Abdullah's email
address. And Abdullah's got a cousin,
Rashid, and Rashid has access to
detonators. And then Rashid's
brother-in-law, you know, whatever. So
then we could call the Germans and say,
"Listen, you have a serious problem in
Dusseldorf. Here's who you need to wrap
up." And then they bust down the door
and they grab everybody and there's no
more al-Qaeda cell in Dusseldorf.
So that was the first thing that he did
for us. The second thing he did for us,
we knew that there was a very bad guy
out there who went by the name Mtar.
We knew from 1996 that Muar was trying
to come up with a plan to use aircraft
as missiles.
>> Okay.
>> In the Philippines, it was called the
Bojinka operation.
The idea was to hijack 14 747s
from Manila airport, fly them across the
Pacific, and fly them into buildings all
up and down the west coast of the United
States.
He has the plans all laid out on a table
and he decides to go out and have lunch.
While he's out at lunch, the cleaning
lady comes to clean the apartment. She
looks at all this and she says, "This
looks like a terrorist attack. I better
call the police." She calls the cops.
The Manila police come, they look at it
and they said, "This looks like a
terrorist attack. We better call the
Philippine Intelligence Service." They
come and they said, "Oh, this looks like
a terrorist attack. We better call the
CIA." So the CIA came and they're like,
"Yeah, this is a terrorist attack being
planned against the Western United
States." By then, Mktad was in the wind.
>> Well, he left for lunch, never came
back.
>> Never came back. I
>> think he was alerted, I'm assuming.
>> Yeah. That all these people are in his
>> Yeah.
>> So,
Ali asked him, "What about we we know
this guy? He wanted to use planes as
missiles just like they did on 911." And
I was laughed at him and said, "You
don't know who Mktar is?" And he said,
"No."
And he said Mktar's name is Khaled Shik
Muhammad.
We had never heard that name before.
And so we start doing our research. Who
is this guy? Khales Shake Muhammad. This
guy graduated from North Carolina State
University.
>> He was here in the States.
>> Yeah.
>> And
>> he came here as an exchange student,
stayed with an American family, went to
North Carolina State, and just came to
hate the United States so much.
>> Do we know why? Do do we know what his
>> you know it was this warped view of
Islam and what Islam should be and and
the bottom line for all these guys is
the closeness of US relations with
Israel. They hate
>> told me
he told me that
that what did it for him? What made him
go from just some guy, you know, who
might throw a rock during a
demonstration to, you know, trying to
assist the
the most dangerous terrorist group in
the world was watching a news report
that showed an Israeli soldier with his
boot on the neck of a Palestinian
grandmother and he decided, "These Jews
have to die."
>> Wow. But that's the whole basis of this.
>> Well, speaking of KSM, were you at the
agency when we caught him?
>> Yeah.
>> Were you a part of that?
>> Uh, no. I had just moved up to the
deputy director's office, but
>> go I I wanted to ask how did we find KSM
intelligence? I'm assuming
>> human source intelligence,
>> not torture.
>> No, no, no, no, no.
Good.
>> Cuz we got him in Pakistan, too. Yeah,
he was in Ra Pendi.
>> Okay. And how long was he on the run
for? Because he was after uh Abu Zabeta,
correct?
>> Yeah, we caught up
in
March of 20 of 2002.
And we caught
KSM. I'm going to say it was August of
2002.
>> Okay.
>> Or September, something like that.
See, but this is listen, if you boil
down the job of the CIA to its simplest
form.
The mission of the CIA is to recruit
spies to steal secrets and then to
analyze those secrets so that the policy
maker can make the best informed policy.
It's really that simple.
You can't rely on NSA
to just
grab everybody's phone calls out of the
air and tell you where the bad guys are.
You have to have a human source that's
in the meeting. That's the only way that
you can destroy these groups.
>> And how [clears throat] do you find
source? What what to find a source on
KSM or because I'm sort of they're
radicals. What are they looking for? or
way out normally or they come to that
some of that like hey this isn't this
isn't right they have that you know
awakening okay
>> sometimes
>> most of the time it's cash on the barrel
head
>> okay
>> you know we had we had a $10 million
uh bounty on a beta
>> $10 million in cash is very heavy
>> very heavy
>> and it it takes multiple you know
>> Yeah I couldn't lift gym bags
>> and we were very happy to deliver the
money. There was 25 million on KSM. Very
happy to give the guys money.
>> Gets delivered right away,
>> immediately.
And if necessary, along with
resettlement
>> and relocating ID,
>> whatever they need to keep the guy safe.
>> Wow. And they'll do that for the rest of
the guy's life
>> or Yeah.
>> They'll set him up. I mean it's not
unusual for us to say all right what
country you want to live in just name
the country
and then we do it
>> even if they said the states you would
re
>> wow
>> it it's you know really really crazy
when you were at the agency
um before you went to uh you know 911
and you know I wanted to talk to that
you spent some time in other Middle
Eastern countries and
>> we're doing this interview, you know,
what was the, you know, before that were
you doing any operations that got the
blood flowing like Abu Zaber doing
interesting stuff or were you doing more
analysis and
>> Oh, no. I mean, my first couple of
tours, Kuwait, uh, Saudi Arabia,
Bahrain, those were analytic tours and
actually Bahrain, I was I was actually
secunded to the State Department. So it
was a legit state department job.
>> Uh it was in
the middle of 97 that I switched to
counterterrorism operations. So I had to
go through the operational training
first and because I was already
mid-career. You didn't have to start at
the beginning with what we call CIA 101.
>> Okay.
>> I was already there for seven and a half
years. I I knew what the CIA did.
>> And so I had I I was able to skip all
that silly entry level stuff and go
straight to operations. Um, instead
instead [clears throat] of being trained
for 18 months, I was trained for six
months.
>> Okay.
>> And then they mix it up between
operational training, um, weapons,
explosives, and counterterrorism
driving.
>> And then surveillance and surveillance
detection. You do a lot a lot of that as
well. I actually became a surveillance
instructor.
>> Okay.
>> At the agency.
>> Any tips for surveillance? I mean, how
do you know if like cuz you know I I
I've all my my my wife will tell you
she's I call it her spidey senses and
you know I've often wondered like hey
how do you tell if you're actually being
followed or surveiled by somebody it's
it's clear [clears throat]
>> yeah you have to constantly be aware of
your surroundings constantly scan your
side view rearview mirrors and there's a
definition a formal definition of
surveillance multiple sightings at time
and distance
>> okay
>> so if you see the same people at
different times of the day at different
locations.
You're under surveillance.
>> You're under surveillance.
>> Okay.
>> So after 97, then I was I went on my
first operational tour to Athens. Okay.
>> In '98. I was there for two years.
>> Went back to headquarters, then back to
the Middle East to Abu Dhabi. Um and
then back to headquarters for 911.
>> Abu Dhabi. What's that like?
>> It's beautiful.
>> It's beautiful, right?
>> It's magnificent.
>> Peaceful country.
>> Oh, very peaceful. I actually prefer Abu
Dhabi to Dubai. Everybody raves about
Dubai. It's Yeah. And Dubai is great.
>> But Abu Dhabi has culture where Dubai
doesn't.
>> I like Doha a lot too. The capital
ofQatar.
>> Yeah, because I'm a big UFC fan and they
had Fight Island and I've was watching I
was like, you know, we need to go to
Dubai. Maybe someday. It is magnificent.
And you can fly direct non-stop from DC,
from New York, from Chicago.
>> Yeah. And they're Americanized in a way.
>> Very much so.
>> Very. Yeah.
>> Are is that a Muslim country still?
>> Yeah.
>> Are the women walking around? Is that
what
>> mostly not? No.
>> Okay.
>> Um the police cars
>> Mhm.
>> are Lamborghinis.
>> Ain't that crazy?
>> It's nuts.
>> Isn't that crazy? The the money that
they have.
So you're at [clears throat] the CIA,
9/11 happens, you leave the CIA and and
I want to talk about, you know, so what
what h what started your trials? Not,
you know, the trial, but what started
the CIA coming after you tribulations?
>> Your tribulations. Yeah.
>> Um when I got back from Pakistan, I was
asked if I wanted to be trained in the
torture techniques. I was one of 14
people approached. I was the only one
who said no. I believed it was illegal.
Clearly, obviously illegal. I [snorts]
don't care what the White House said, it
was illegal.
>> Was the redheaded devil trained in the
torture program?
>> She was the founder, the creator of the
torture program.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> And so,
um, I objected to it internally. I said,
"This is immoral. It's illegal. It's
unethical. We shouldn't be in the
practice of torturing people."
And in retrospect, I was right. That's
why literally nobody has been brought to
justice because everything they said,
they said as a result of torture and not
a word of it can be used against them in
court.
>> Are you serious?
>> None of KSM Abu and we'll get to because
I I know mom, you know, cuz uh I think
you were talking to Abu Zaba's attorney
>> or or had him on your podcast or or
whatnot. Will those guys ever be
sentenced?
>> Never. They'll never be sentenced
because they can never be charged with a
crime.
>> Will they ever get out?
>> No.
>> Beta might.
>> Uh at the very end of the Biden
administration, they were pretty deep in
talks to release him. You know, finally
acknowledging that he was just the wrong
guy. He's been in prison for 23 years.
>> Wow.
>> And the only thing that they were
waiting on was they were they were
trying to find a country that would
accept him. And then Trump won. And so
four more years he's just gonna have to
sit it out and wait.
>> What's his day-to-day life like now? Do
you think
>> it's like Groundhog Day? There's there's
no more torture going on at Guantanamo,
but it's just like Groundhog Day. You
know, one funny thing was when it
appeared
that a deal was was going to be made,
Khalik Muhammad,
Ramsey Benes,
Amar, Alaluch, there might have been one
more. They were going to plead guilty to
um
>> war crimes,
>> terrorism.
>> Terrorism.
>> Yep. and terrorism and conspiracy to use
a weapon of mass destruction
and they were going to agree to life
without parole.
So the government took the death penalty
off the table and the only thing that
they asked was if they could stay in
Guantanamo because the weather's so
good. They didn't want to go to the
supermax in Florence, Colorado. And then
Biden's um secretary of defense threw
the whole deal out. Why do you think
that is?
>> Because he wasn't a part of the
negotiations and he was pissed off that
he didn't get to say
>> what to Okay.
>> Yeah. So, he threw it out.
>> The attorneys sued
>> and the attorneys lost. So, now there's
no deal. We're back to square one. We're
back to where we were in 2002.
>> Who's paying to house them at Guantanamo
Bay? We are.
>> Yeah, of course.
>> How many prisoners are at Guantanamo
Bay? I think it's down to like
and about half of them are awaiting
resettlement. Yeah.
>> Just waiting for other countries to
accept them.
>> Really?
>> You don't think these guys would
recommmit?
>> No.
>> KSM, you don't think,
>> you know, at the max we had over 700 and
almost every single one of them was
innocent of any crime.
>> Are you Are you serious?
>> Yeah. You see, let's say you and I live
in Afghanistan.
>> Yeah.
>> And I borrow money from you, right?
>> I don't want to pay you back. So, I call
the Americans. I say, "Hey, uh, yeah,
this guy over here, al-Qaeda, they grab
you. We never see you again, and I don't
have to pay back that loan."
>> Wow.
>> Mhm.
>> And we just wanted a pound of flesh.
>> They were innocent. So, most have been
released. There are about 17 who will
never be released.
Even in the Senate torture report, in
one of the footnotes,
it said that Abu Zuba shall never be
released ever. He shall never be able to
speak to the media and when he dies,
he'll be cremated and his ashes will be
thrown into the Caribbean.
>> Why don't they want him talking to the
media?
>> Because we
>> Well, well, yeah. No, I'm I'm being
sarcastic. He drew um pictures
of himself being tortured
>> and they classified the pictures top
secret.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I've heard stories about putting
cockroaches and a diaper on him and put
him in a coffin and [clears throat]
>> for weeks just dump cockroaches.
>> I just don't think how anybody could
think you would get somebody to I would
tell you what the [__] ever you wanted
to hear just to make it stop.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean,
>> and that's what he did. That's why most
of the information that he gave after
Ali Safan was all nonsense.
>> What was the other guy involved in the
torture program from the CIA? Not John
Brennan. Jose or
>> Jose Rodriguez.
>> What's that guy? He retired from the
CIA. Decorated, right?
>> He lives down in uh he lives down in um
St. Augustine, Florida, next to Rick
Prao, who was the head of the special
activities division. Um they lived
literally next door to each other. And
um he's living fat and happy on his
>> They'll never be brought to justice.
>> No. Never. Never. Never.
>> But we all and I'm not making this about
religion. I'm a Catholic. But we all
will face judgment someday.
>> Whatever you believe.
>> Sure we will. I I believe that Jose
Rodriguez is a psychopath.
>> Psychopath.
>> He if you look if you look at the at the
events that took place over the course
of his career, he was on the wrong side
of the issue. dozens of times,
reprimanded countless times, and then
responsible for the torture program. And
he wants America to think that he's some
kind of hero.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, you you do an interview with Brian
Ross, right?
And when you get called for that
interview, what are what you're your he
says you you know you tortured Abu Zada,
you know what what made you agreed to
talk to him without a
>> reason why I agreed to talk to Brian
Ross and I I made a mistake. I made a
couple of mistakes. One, I didn't have
my attorney with me.
>> I would never do that again.
>> But two, the information that I had been
given at the agency was also wrong. It
was that Aba Beta had been waterboarded
once and he broke. He wasn't
waterboarded once. He was waterboarded
83 times. So, I was wrong about that.
But that was the lie that was
circulating among us. But I actually
wasn't going to talk to Brian. And then
in the days after he called me,
President Bush gave a press conference
and one of the reporters asked him about
torture and he looks in the camera and
he goes, "We do not torture."
I said to my wife, "He's a bald-faced
liar."
Just look at the American people in the
eye. Lying.
And then a couple of days later, it was
a Friday, he walks out the south portico
of the White House, the back door of the
White House to walk to the helicopter
and fly to Camp David. And a reporter
shouts a question at him. And he turns
and he says, "Well, if there is torture,
it's because of a rogue CIA officer." I
said to my wife, "Brian Ross's source is
at the White House and they're going to
try to pin this on me. I'm going to
defend myself." And so I decided I'd
give Brian Ross his interview and I
would just simply tell the truth and
that's what I did.
>> And
after that you get a job working for
John Kerry which you you talk about. I
mean and what is uh before we're getting
to this you know what is Carrie like?
You know you've been around all these
politicians.
>> What is Carrie like when there's no
cameras? There's
>> you you spent time with him in a room
like this. I'm sure there's nobody but
you two. What would you describe his
leadership style and personality like?
>> A couple nights before I left for
prison,
>> okay?
>> I I emailed Carrie at his private email
and I said, "Senator, I'm begging you.
Please help me. Ask the president to
commute my sentence. The conviction
would still stand, but I could work and
and put food on the table for my family.
I have five kids.
>> Wow.
>> And he writes me back and all he said
was, "Please do not ever attempt to
contact me again."
>> That's John Kerry.
>> Wow.
>> Wow. He married a Hines, I believe.
Right.
>> He married Senator John Hines's widow.
>> The ketchup factory people from
Pittsburgh.
>> Yeah. She was married to John Hines, who
was the grandson of the founder of Hines
Ketchup.
>> Yeah. And um I mean he was worth close
to a billion dollars and died in a plane
crash
>> and as soon as he died Carrie just
zeroed right in on her.
>> He talks about uh you know the
environment but yet he flies his private
jet all over.
>> When I was working for him he bought
this yacht and it wasn't even just a
yacht. It was like an oceangoing ship,
right? He represents Massachusetts
represented Massachusetts in the in the
Senate and he docked the yacht in Rhode
Island. Why? Because Massachusetts had a
yacht tax.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, you're worth a billion dollars.
Pay your [__] taxes. Yeah.
>> So,
the press just beat him up over it. And
a couple of us went to the to the uh
chief of staff.
We said, "This is a very bad look. Just
tell him pay the tax."
And so, this dragged on for a couple of
weeks. Finally, he just took the yacht
back to Massachusetts and he paid the
tax. But, you know, are all rich people
that cheap? Just pay your tax.
>> Yeah, we have to.
>> He He bought everybody in the office a
Christmas present one time.
Uh, it was Christmas of 2009 and it was
a bottle of wine and uh I didn't
recognize the wine and I've I've
subscribed for 25 years to Wine
Spectator magazine. I love it. Okay.
>> My wife and I bought we built a a wine
seller, a climate controlled wine seller
in our in our house. [clears throat] We
know about wine.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, I was like, I never saw this wine
before.
>> And I know I shouldn't have, but I
Googled it.
>> Yeah.
>> It's a $10 bottle of wine
>> wine.
>> Like, really?
>> You're worth a billion dollars and and
you [__] Did he try to say, "Oh,
that's a $100 bottle of wine.
>> Merry Christmas." Thank you.
So, John Brennan, how does he get to
where, hey, he says, "Charge him." How
do we get there? What What he just
didn't like you? You and him didn't get
along.
>> John and I never liked each other. I met
John in 1990. I didn't like him. He
didn't like me, but I stayed on my side
of the room and he stayed on his. Um
it's a very long story but the the
upshot is that there was a wave of
retirements in 2007
where you know the war on terror terror
was going to drag on for
>> burned out people were burned out
>> burned out ready to go you've already
done 30 35 years 911's 5 years behind us
time to retire
of the hundreds of people that retired
Half of them went to the John McCain
campaign. Half of them went to the
Hillary Clinton campaign.
John Brennan was literally the only one
who went to the Barack Obama campaign.
>> Okay.
>> So, he became Obama's guy.
Uh when Obama won the race, Obama
initially named him CIA director, but
the liberals just threw a fit and so he
withdrew that nomination and made
Brennan deputy national security adviser
for counterterrorism
>> because you don't need a confirmation.
>> Correct. Exactly. And then four years
later, the liberals have forgotten why
they were so mad. Then he became the CIA
director. But John was the most powerful
national security figure in the Obama
administration. Yeah.
>> And so
he insisted that the Justice Department
prosecute me for my uh my revelations
about torture.
>> When you find out they're coming after
you, what are you thinking? I mean,
you're a patriot. I mean, and and and
and I and I mean that. And the CIA is
you protect us. You do. You do things
that keep us safe. When I'm a kid, my
children now, my wife, even me, you
there's something going on. You You've
been there. you done at across the world
that could really hurt the American
people and you handle it and we never
hear about it, you know, and you don't
get any glory and and and I mean no
disrespect. That's cool.
>> Yeah.
>> They ask you even in the in the
application pro uh process if you're
comfortable not receiving recognition
for your victories and everybody's like,
"Yeah, nobody cares."
>> Yeah. So, what are you thinking though?
They're they're coming after you. You
think, you know, I mean,
>> my head was spinning
>> because you never been You've probably
never had a speeding ticket or anything
in your [__] life.
>> Nothing. Nothing.
>> And if you did, I'm sure you could make
it go away like that.
>> I never did.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um I I I couldn't believe it. But they
they hit me with a concrete block from
the beginning. I was facing 45 years in
prison.
>> Holy [__] And so I mean the the most
important conversation that you have
with yourself is
should I kill myself? You maybe I should
45 years. I can't. I'm I'm 50 years old.
>> Your kids are grown up.
>> Am I in prison?
>> Yeah. 100. You're Yeah. Yeah. Your
wife's moved on and probably have
somebody else. Your kids don't know you.
I mean,
>> but my wife was such a great supporter
>> and I I mean 70 former CIA and FBI
officers came together to support me.
>> No kidding.
>> They signed a letter to the president
asking him to to pardon me before I ever
went to trial.
>> And this is Obama
>> under Obama. And um and I was blessed
with the best attorneys in Washington.
>> Yes. See, um, and side note, so you had
Plato
>> Cacher that, so once I heard of your
story, well, heard who you were and and
like you were on a podcast. We're
watching the uh documentary on A&E about
Monica Lewinsky and all of a sudden I
heard that name and I'm like, what the
[__] Thank you. You know, so and
>> was a killer in when I mean a killer, I
meant a [__] defense attorney. That
guy was a shark. A [__] shark. He was
described in the Washington Post when my
attorneys announced that they were
representing
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> It was Plato Cateras uh
uh Mark McDougall from Aken Gump and
Strauss and Bob uh
>> I don't know. I I
>> What What's wrong with me?
>> Please, you have to edit this.
>> Go. Yeah.
Um
Bob Trout. Okay.
>> Okay. So my my three lead attorneys were
Plato Catereras and Bob Trout of Trout
Cacheras and Mark McDougall from Aken
Gump and Strauss. Mark Mark was the the
director of white collar defense at Aken
Gump which is one of the biggest law
firms in the world.
>> Okay.
>> Not just in America.
>> Defense law criminal law or only
>> criminal defense.
>> Okay. probably thou I mean I don't know
they're probably $5,000 $10,000 an hour
>> at the time. Yeah. They were $2,000 an
hour which I didn't have.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but Plato said to me from the very
beginning, "This this case is not about
John Kiryaku.
This case is far bigger than John
Kuryaku. This case is about silencing
every national whistleblower, national
security whistleblower in America."
>> Because you were before Snowden, right?
>> Oh yeah. In fact, Snowden told the New
York Times that I inspired him.
>> Okay.
>> To do his whistleblow.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. Crazy. His dad came to prison to
visit me.
>> No [__]
>> To thank me.
>> Have you talked about that on a podcast
at all?
>> I may have mentioned.
>> No. No. I just So, you get charged. You
get Plato. And you know, I've been
arrested. Go ahead.
>> Well, I was facing 45 years and then
after like 10 months,
>> were you out on bail?
Yeah.
>> Okay. House arrest, bail, or any home
confinement or
>> No, not home confinement. No,
personal recgnizance.
>> Oh, they really left you out on ROI
>> cuz they knew this was [__] [__]
This whole situation.
>> So
after 10 months, DOJ came to us and
said,
>> "Take a plea to espionage. Do 10 years."
And I was an [__] that day. I said,
"I'm not doing 10 minutes."
So, um, that was on a Monday. On
Wednesday, they said, "Eight years
espionage."
>> Normally, they don't come down.
Normally, they go up.
>> Wednesday or Friday, they said 5 years
final offer. I said, "Forget it." And
Plato said to me, "I've been an attorney
in this town for 52 years, and I have
never seen them come down in time." And
I said, 'Wh are they doing that? And he
said, ' Because they have a [__] case
and they know it's [__] Just like that.
He said, 'We going to trial.' I was
like, God, that is exactly what I wanted
to hear.
So, we turned everything down. And Plato
said, we tried to get him to to consider
the offer, but he wants to go to trial
and he wants to testify on his own
behalf, which I didn't. Um, and if he
testifies, you know, he may accidentally
talk about some war crimes and crimes
against humanity that he's witnessed in
his 15 years at the CIA. And then they
were like, okay, three and a half years.
And I said, "No."
And they said, "Best and final offer,
30 months. You do 23."
I had until noon the next day to make a
decision. My wife and I stayed up all
night long
talking, researching.
There were two articles in the Harvard
Law Review that said the law that I was
charged under should never have been
passed in the first place. It was
unconstitutional.
So, I sent the attorneys a letter. Uh,
sorry. I sent the attorneys an email at
six o'clock in the morning and I said,
"Been up all night. I'm turning down the
30 months. Let's go for let's go for
trial."
Bob Trout emailed me back and he said,
"Put on a pot of coffee. We're on the
way over." This is 6 o'clock in the
morning. They come to the house at seven
and it was Plato, Bob, Mark, and the top
next level down lawyer. I had 11
lawyers.
>> No [__]
>> Four of them came to the house. John
Hunley was his name. Awesome guy. So
Plato was the first one through the door
and he gets right in my face and he
says, "You stupid son of a [__] Take
the [__] deal." Like that. Wow.
>> I said, "You're the one that told me to
go to trial." He said, "I only said that
to make your morale higher." [laughter]
>> And then Bob Trout, who is just such a
lovely southern gentleman,
he kind of pulls me aside and he says,
"If you were my own brother, I would beg
you to take this deal."
And then Mark Mark McDougall was the one
who I I liked I liked and trusted all of
them. I liked and trusted Mark the most.
He and I just kind of connected.
>> Totally nononsense guy and one of the
most brilliant legal minds anywhere in
America.
He gets right up in my face and he he's
like seething with anger and he says,
"You know what your problem is? Your
problem is you think this is about
justice and it's not about justice. It's
about mitigating damage. Take the deal.
And I said, "Mark, if I don't take the
deal and I'm convicted, what am I
realistically looking at?" And he said,
"12 to 18 years. Take the deal."
And so I took the deal.
>> And you're sentenced. You You plead
guilty, whatnot, cuz I think you said
>> you brought to all the espionage charges
cuz I hadn't committed espionage. And
you had hired they had hired a jury
consultant, right? That told you if it
because of the count
>> I hired.
>> You you Okay. Okay. I'm sorry.
>> My best friend's wife, her uncle was OJ
Simpson's jury consult.
>> No kidding.
>> And he had also done George Zimmerman,
the Trayvon Martin case. He had done uh
one of the Kennedys that had allegedly
raped some woman.
>> The guy has quite literally never lost a
case. So, we get him admitted as as an
adviser, as a legal adviser, and they
give him a security clearance. He comes
up, goes through the whole 15,000 pages
of classified discovery. We're all
meeting in the conference room at Plato
Cacheras's uh law firm, and the jury
consultant says, "If we were in any
other district in America, I'd say,
let's go for it. We're going to win this
thing. This case is shit." He said, 'But
the Eastern District of Virginia, your
jury is going to be made up of people
from the CIA or with relatives at the
CIA, DoD, Homeland Security, FBI,
intelligence community contractors. You
don't have a prayer. He said, "Take the
deal." I
>> think that was a part of their strategy,
DOJ, to have it in. Yeah.
>> And it wasn't just for me.
>> They charge almost everybody, every
national security.
>> So Snowden in his turn. He's already
been charged in the Eastern District of
Virginia.
>> And Julian Assange was in the Eastern
District of Virginia. And
>> Zacharias
Mousawi, the 20th hijacker, whatever his
name was. And uh Oh, there are a couple
of other people. They're all charged in
EDBA. They call it the espionage court
because no national security defendant
has ever won a case there.
>> Yeah.
>> Never.
>> And you plead guilty. And what month is
that? I I changed my plea in October of
2012.
I was formally sentenced
in January of 2012. And I reported to
prison on February 28th, 20.
>> So, they gave you a little bit of time
with your family before you went to
prison.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm sure you're nervous, right? What
is that time, if you don't mind talking
about it, before you leave for prison?
Like,
>> tell you the truth. Yeah. You would
think that I would be a nervous wreck.
to tell the truth. I felt a sense of
relief
>> that it's going to be over.
>> It's going to be over and there's
there's an end in sight. I mean, 30
months is the max. I'm going to get out
at 23 months with good behavior, but I
stood a chance at 6 months of home
confinement, which I didn't get because
they screwed me. But
>> I thought, you know, I could I could do
23 months on my head.
>> Yeah. You were in [__] Pakistan. Some
of the places that you can't tell us
about what
>> [clears throat]
>> You have children and you know were all
of them at home still at at
>> No. Um my three youngest were still at
home. My two oldest were in college.
>> How was that? You know cuz I'm a father.
>> Terrible
>> there. You know even me this tough guy.
Um hell I cry sometimes leaving my kids
for 5 days to go away to work.
>> But uh I'm sure that was hard for you.
part was
>> the kids were little. They were like
nine
nine, seven, and one.
And so the hardest part was trying to
explain to them. So, you know, trying to
put it in in kids language, I said, you
know, I've been fighting with the FBI
for a long time now, and I'm sorry to
say that I lost the fight. So, I'm going
to have to go to Pennsylvania,
and I'm going to teach bad guys how to
get their high school diploma. And when
I finish that, I'm going to come back
and everything's going to be good again.
And they accepted that. It was hard and
it was a little confusing, but they
accepted it. And then my wife would
bring them up to the prison every month
to visit me. And there was a sign on one
of the doors that said inmates only. And
so they got seated in the in the
visiting room and I came through the
door. And when I sat down, you know,
hugs and kisses and they want to sit on
my lap. And my my nine-year-old, then
nine-year-old
said, "Dad, what does inmate mean?" And
I said, "Prisoner?"
Not thinking that the sign's on the
door. And he said, "Wait a minute. Are
you a teacher here or are you a prisoner
here?"
And I was like
I said, "I'm a prisoner, buddy, but it's
it's going to be over soon and
everything's going to be good."
That was the hardest thing.
>> Yeah. For for sure. So you you you get
to prison in in Lorettto. A I guess John
Brennan kind of gave you the finger
there.
>> Yeah. In fact, at sentencing, my
attorneys asked the judge to send me to
the minimum security work camp and the
justice department said they had no
objection and she says, "Okay, minimum
security camp." When I arrived, they put
me in the prison.
>> How did they do that? Did they fudge the
paper?
>> No. The CIA called DOJ. Remember, the
prosecutors are different from the
Bureau of Prisons. And the prosecutors
are different from the FBI. Yeah.
>> So John Brennan just had to make a call
to Eric Holder and said, "Fuck this guy.
Put him in the actual prison.
>> Do me a favor. Do me a solid. I owe you
one."
>> Yes, he did.
>> Wow. And what was your time like in in
in prison?
>> Monotonous. Um, I
I was um determined to
use my CIA training to stay safe and at
the top of the social heap, which I did
very successfully. I made strategic
alliances, which
>> even in a low security federal prison is
prison. Okay.
>> Yeah. Even with minimum, there's no such
thing as club fed. I hate when people
say that. It's a thing for me.
>> Yeah. Cuz my uncle went to federal
prison. I don't know if you know where
this one There's one out in Ohio.
>> Which one?
>> Oh my god. I knew you were going to ask
me that.
>> Is it the one by Youngstown that's
pedophile?
>> Yeah. Well, he's not a pedophile. He
stole [__] checks out of mailboxes.
>> But he always told me, "Hey, if you're
going to go to prison, you do a federal
[__] crime." Well, I mean, I mean my
very [__] up, but anyway. And I said,
"What?" He he was a mechanic and they
got him a job in town or whatever he
would and they played softball. They
actually went and [__] had like
softball tournaments at other prisons
minimum
>> and and I says I said to my grand one
day
>> and I'm like third I said so he goes and
steals checks
out of mailboxes cashes them and he gets
to go play [__] soft gets to go to
summer camp and she says well he says
that's why he always and he said he
always said if he was going to do
something to go to prison he'd make sure
it'd be in federal prison. One of my
cellmates was a guy who committed some
stupid federal crime and did a year or
two, whatever it was. Uh but he was
homeless in Pittsburgh. He he used to
live under a bridge uh on the Alageney
River.
>> Yeah.
>> And when the weather would turn,
>> he would violate his probation every
year and they'd send it back for 6
months, you know, as a violator. and
he's like, "Six months, got a warm bed,
got medical care, free food. I get out
in the spring, do the whole thing again
next year."
>> Yeah. So, when do you start meeting
mafiosas? The my channel, most of my
guests are former mafiosas. Uh, so when
do you get introduced to the Italians in
the the mafia?
>> I think they're about six weeks.
>> Okay. And um I got word from another one
of the guys that that one of them wanted
to see me. [clears throat]
So I went down there, introduced myself.
Couldn't have been any nicer.
>> Who was he?
>> Um he was from one of the he was from
the Philadelphia family, the scarf of
the Bruno Scarlet family.
>> And you were eating with some Gambinos,
Vanos, Genevies.
>> I ended up to make a long story short, I
ended up being kind of adopted by the uh
by the Italians.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> We had the boss of the Gambino family.
We had the boss and under boss of the
Petriarcha family from Boston.
>> We had the the number three from the
Banano family. Uh but there were a lot
of Gambinos. There were a lot of Philly
guys.
>> Any Genevese?
>> Yeah. Uh he was the boss of the port of
Newark when I first arrived. He and I
used to go to church together.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Okay. And [clears throat] so
you're Did the CIA ever try to mess with
you in prison?
>> Yeah, they did. Really?
>> Yeah. Uh Mark McDougall, one of my
attorneys that I mentioned a moment ago,
warned me that this was going to happen.
He pulled me aside right before I left
for prison and he said, "Listen, they're
really pissed off that you have such a
short sentence
>> and they're going to try to set you up
and they're going to add charges, so be
very, very careful." I was like, "Okay,
all right." So, I kind of filed it in
the back of my head. One day I'm in my
cell and there was a an Afghan-American
guy. Uh he was a pharmacist but he had
an oxy problem. So he was doing six
years. Nice guy. So he comes up to me.
He goes, "Hey, John, there's there's a
new guy wants to meet you." I said, "Oh,
yeah." He said, "Yeah, he's the
spokesman for the Taliban." I said,
"That guy from New Jersey." And he said,
"Yeah." I said, "I've read about that
guy. He's he's a rat. that that's how he
got such a sweetheart sentence. He he
ratted out everybody. He was the Taliban
spokesman in the United States.
>> Okay.
>> I said, "No, I'm not interested in
meeting him."
And he goes, "Oh, okay. I'll tell him."
So, another couple of days pass. I
happen to be out in the yard just
walking around the track and here's this
guy walking right toward me, beard down
to his waist. He's got his hand out like
this. And I went like this and I said,
"Don't [__] touch me." Like that. And
as I'm looking at him, I happen to look
to the side of him and one of the guards
is on the outside of the fence with a
camera with a long-distance lens going.
So I had my hands up and I said, "Don't
[__] touch me and don't ever try to
speak to me." He said, "Come on, man. We
have a lot in common." I said, "We have
nothing in common other than I tried to
kill people like you. Get the [__] away
from me." And he's like, "Oh, come on.
Come on." And then finally he walked
away. And then the guard had nothing
nothing to send back to the CIA or DOJ.
>> So
you you get out, you know, what what's
it like your you know what what what was
your first couple of days reaclimating
back into
>> Well, that's that's a problem. People
think that you can just step back into
>> [__] no. I mean, I I I've never done it,
had to do it, but there's no way. You
are a character, I'm sure, of a creature
by habit, by routine, and I'm sure your
routine changed drastically from home
life to prison, and now you're back in
home life. I'm sure it took a while to
get readapted.
>> I had I had a couple of months of uh
three months of uh house arrest, which
means you cannot leave the confines of
the four walls of your house. You can't
go in the front yard or the backyard or
the stoop inside the house.
>> You go crazy.
>> That's worse than [__] prison, right?
>> Way worse than prison. Way worse.
>> And then they call you quite literally
24 hours a day to give your name, your
prisoner number, and your social
security number because they want to
make sure that you haven't left.
So, um on top of that, you got to go
into this [__]
uh what do you call it? the halfway
house and check in once a week and then
drug testing twice a week. I've never
taken a drug in my life. I'm happy to
waste as much of your time and the
government's money as I possibly can,
but you're wasting my time, too. So, it
was
it was very difficult to transition back
to home life. Very difficult.
But and the bigger problem for me was I
just couldn't find a job. Nobody is
willing to hire a a convicted felon.
>> Nobody.
>> And so, you know, I I briefly worked for
a a think tank in Washington just doing
criminal justice issues.
>> What is a think tank? Um
>> it's a group of academics that, you
know, writes papers and gives about the
issues of the day.
>> And uh I did that for about a year and
then I just realized
this just isn't going to work. I'm going
to have to work for myself. And then I
ended up getting an offer for a radio
show. I I took that. I did the radio
show for seven years. And then that led
to podcast after podcast after podcast,
which led to my own TV show. And now
I've been out of prison for
13 years. Is that right?
>> No.
11 years.
Yes. I've been out for 11 years. And um
yeah, I have my own successful podcasts.
I have my own successful TV show. I
write columns. I just finished writing
my ninth book. And um and I I made the
right decision to just work for myself.
>> Yeah.
>> That's really the only way you can s you
can succeed.
>> Yeah. How much longer you got, bud?
>> It's it's almost 10.
>> Yeah.
>> And I got to catch that early flight to
LA.
>> You tell me. I mean
>> Yeah. Can we wrap it up?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, now that you're
doing your podcast, you know, and you
you sat down and and spoke with me, uh,
where where can people find you?
>> Oh, thanks for asking. So, um, I've got
a website, johnkuryaku.com,
but where I post most everything. I
mean, I'm on Facebook and X and LinkedIn
and Instagram and all that stuff, but
I've got uh a podcast called called uh
Deep Focus. That's on YouTube. I have
one every day called Deprogram. Monday
through Friday that's on YouTube and
Rumble and one on Apple podcast called
John Kuryaku's Dead Drop which goes into
granular detail about my whole life in
the CIA.
>> Okay. Well, thank you. Appreciate it.